foreign
so it's about the observance day
um so now at that time it being the
repositor day visaka
went to the blessed one in the middle of
the day and on arrival having bowed down
to him set to one side
as she was sitting there the blessed one
set her
well now be Psycho why are you coming in
the middle of the day today I'm
observing the oppositor
and the Buddha says visaka they are
these three are positives
they are poster of the Cowherd the one
who watches the other people's cows
Shepherd the shepherd
be a poster of the Giants
and their poster of the noble ones
so what the what is their poster of the
cow herd just as when a cow heard
uh let's call it the shepherd
Returns the Sheep to their owners in the
evening he reflects today the Sheep
wandered to that spot and this drank at
this spot and that tomorrow they will
wander to that spot and this will drink
at this spot and that in the same way
there is the case where a certain person
observing the Earth poster reflex
today I ate this sort of food and that
sort of food tomorrow I will eat that
sort of food and this sort of food he
spends the day with an awareness
imbued with with that covetousness with
that greed such as the poster of the
shepherd the psycho who's basically just
thinking about centrality what he had
what he will have I will have it working
for it planning for it that is what he's
observing that the observance of his
mind those values are values that his
mind is observing so that's why it's the
it's the type of repositor is the type
of observance
what did I have where did I have it how
I had it what I more of it will I get
more of it more of the same new stuff
sensuality like she drink here eat there
yeah so it's the it's the the way normal
people well it's like whenever sorry
yeah uninstructed the mind would do yeah
that's that's the that's what's the
that's what the values are pleasure
protecting the pleasure getting more
pleasure avoiding pain yeah like
thinking about the past Pleasures how
can I yeah more of the same more of the
same and that does require you know
people like take it for granted they
don't necessarily
develop self-awareness but if they would
become self-aware they would realize
that that requires planning and
observing and and contemplating and
deciding and and actually it involves
quite a lot of work yeah sure
so it is a type of observance
yeah and it's that anticipation
that the practice of and anticipating oh
yeah that's that's what that's what's
like a driving force it's that
anticipation the ride
is what gives you the energy and the
inspiration to do it
if you were to immediately reflect on
the results
that you experienced so many times
before like results of the satisfa of
allowing your senses to feed carelessly
when they want to you realize well
actually that's
it's not that much it's not that great
I've done it before
but it's approaching the idea of results
through the mind of anticipation then
it's always like infinite pleasure
promise although you know it's not you
know it's going to last for a bit
experienced it many times but you forget
or you don't put the result first you
put your anticipation first and then you
can't resist the right
although you know it's going to have a
very limited result so your anticipation
becomes the driving force that's exactly
what it is yeah that's the Delight in
sexuality is the gratification of
central not getting what you want
is allowing the light to be first it's
how you gratify your senses
now well you have to be able to reflect
on this now this is what I'm cultivating
anticipation anticipation anticipation
so even if I get that and more of what I
anticipated what I'm cultivating the
whole time is anticipation anticipation
so what I will have in the future for
sure is anticipation
so even if I get the content of what I'm
anticipating yeah exactly that
anticipation the mind of anticipation
overrides everything that I would get
particularly yes specifically yeah
whatever food whatever is pleasurable
experience my mind well it's that's that
is exactly when the winner talks about
understanding the gratification of
centrality it's that Chanda the Delight
the Zeal the anticipation
it's not the contact with the agreeable
object that's not the gratification
gratification you're already gratifying
your sensuality by allowing the
anticipation to be first by accepting it
by welcoming it by delighting it further
that's the inspiration the uplifting the
joy towards that's already your
towards that's already your
gratification of centrality and then
everything else that follows through the
framework of anticipation is just
proliferation of that gratification so
that's why it's never ending because the
framework of anticipation yeah can last
infinitely you just have to keep it
going just keep finding new stuff here and
just keep finding new stuff here and
there
classification is that anticipation
that means Zeal it means Delight can
mean like all of these you know can be a
good deal but it can mean bad deal like
you you're very inspired anticipating
full of energy full of full of uh like
effort and and ready to do the work to
get central pleasures
that's already your gratification not
later on touching the result of the
central pleasure that's Pleasant what
people usually get is satisfaction my
desires no no your satisfaction began
when you jumped onto the the that kind
of the pressure that is sort of
um effortless sort of uh
ride of anticipation and that's why
sensuality is intoxicating because it
masks all the effort you are actually doing
all the effort you are actually doing
but you are unaware of it because it
feels effortless
if there is no anticipation towards the
sense pleasure
even like you know not so difficult
tasks feel like depressing feel heavy
feel pointless feel hard to do
but all you need to do is put that like
charity on the top as waiting for you
the carrots the carrots yeah and then it
just becomes absolutely effortless while
in reality you do much more as a result
of that
anticipation nothing else that's when
some suitors you know the Buddha talked
about danger of that gratification
dangerous sensuality he talked about it
different contexts obviously always are
having the same principle but in some
suit as he said the danger of sensuality
is having to work fields sweat and due
the heat to earn the money to to get
married to have family to protect to
work with that's the danger and you
realize yeah that's all kind of what
your anticipation is based on and you're
doing all these things hard work
unnecessary work because it's all kind
of
are bonded together with this idea of
the great result that is only great
because you put anticipation first so
that's already your gratification
centrality you don't put the
anticipation first you allow the
reflection to recognize everything you
do in account of sensuality and then at
the same time you see the end result of
that sensuality that that carrot and
then you realize oh this is not a good
deal but it's easy to forget
if you put the anticipation first and
the carrot second and the the sex
pleasure second and then everything else
becomes invisible and it's just this
effortless inspired Zeal that you're
just flying weightless on
and that's exactly why sensuality is
intoxicating because it just feels
you're not doing anything it's like down
to you
it's enjoyable because it's effortless
but if that is actually completely the
opposite of the effortless
all the effort before in the middle and
after they will follow
it's a strain major stranger it's a
Perpetual strain that it's not felt
because of the perversion of the order
the version of the other in this case is
putting the dissipation first
and then allowing that to sort of become
the framework for everything else you do
and then it masks the weight of it
that's the trick of it nothing else so
don't put the anticipation first
don't act out of it first endure it
descend The Wider background while
you're anticipating and then things will
just fall into place
the the lack of satisfaction discussed
the parallel the the actual ugliness of
it and then your anticipation will just
fizzle out and that's when gratification
has been understood and abandoned
you don't have Zeal anymore on account
of that direction of sense desires
and that's a good chance good deal good
desire so
so
you see the danger of anticipation as I
was saying
that your whole your whole mind is just
driven by that you know you can't stop
yourself do you you can see that the places it's
do you you can see that the places it's
taking you
yeah the states of mind that is dragging
you through but you can't stop
having that craving and cultivating
their craving yeah no that's the thing
you can't stop having it
but you can stop cultivating it by not
putting it first by enduring it and then
broadening the picture as I said and
then you will stop having it eventually
when you stop feeding it it will die out
but you also you can see the future
dangers you know yeah exactly imagine if
I keep doing this for 50 years yeah yeah
no no of course of course
um if I keep doing this for 50 years
this craving
fantasizing going after the essential
Pleasures eventually I'll get old and
everything will calm down no no what
happens is
the longer you do it the stronger the
craving becomes the weaker you become
and what is the poster of the Giants
they are the contemplatives called the
Giants and the gunthers they get their
disciples to undertake the following
practice they say here my good man lay down your
they say here my good man lay down your
weapons with regard to beings who live
more than a hundred leagues to the east
to the west to the north to the South
thus they get their disciple to
undertake kindness and compassion to
some beings not to others
that's different to kind of giants as I
know as you know they they want to
protect all beings but anyway they're
finished on the opposite or and on the
opposer today they get their disciple to
undertake the following practice they
say here my good men having taken off
all your clothing say this I'm nothing
to anyone anywhere and nobody is
anything to me anyway
yeah the form was one of the foremost
views of an outsider yeah I'm nothing
towards anyone nothing's no one's mine
I'm not anybody's
so they get that person to say that to
declare that yet in spite of that his
parents know him know of him that this
is our child and he knows them that
these are hypones his wives and children
know him that this is our husband and
father and he knows them and these are
my wives and children and someone with
his workers so
in other words he
he's not practicing what he's declaring
he hasn't been practicing and he has no
plans of doing it he's just declaring it
because he's in the presence of a
that holds such a positive so he's just
going along with it for whatever
benefits he believes you're gonna get
from it yeah some special that's no
different at all special practice
thus at at that time when he should be
persuaded to undertake truthfulness he's
persuaded to undertake he's like
falsehood yeah at that at the end of the
night he uh resumes the consumption of
his belongings he takes back his
clothing and things and he's he's given
up and nothing's his even though they
aren't given back to him
and he gave them up this counts as
stealing it says yeah yeah I tell you
such is there a post of the Giants when
they're supposed to have the giant is
undertaken yeah so he gave the example
to Giants because obviously it was
probably prominent at the time but uh
you could see the principle of that
is basically taking on the practice
uh superficially and I think that's sort
of what he describes the Meadows pretty
much most of the temples today where
people go and take the precepts because
they offer the food so they go through
the motion of chanting the precepts
declaring the precepts knowing even
beforehand that the moment they leave
the monastery
pieces won't applying to them they'll
carry on drinking or whatever else
but it's done by both so the monks are
encouraging exactly like giants come
good man take the precept it's good for
you you make Merit and they do so both
while knowing it's just going to be for
the duration of the chant and maybe till
the end of the day until they leave the
monastery then they go back to their own
life normally nothing has changed
so it's not really no positive but it's
a title of positive as you can see like
proposed on the surface
yeah uh which is worse
because it's it's even more dishonest
because many people do genuinely believe
certainly traditional Buddhists that by
simply by taking the precepts without
the intention of keeping them they are
accruing Merit somehow somewhere because
look I am doing this yeah I'm clean
clean yeah yeah it's like it's a form of
cleansing yeah take take your clothes
put these clothes wash your hair you
know bow to the four directions whatever
Giants were doing or other problems
that's exactly yeah just going through
the motions that obviously are kind of
held together with the belief of O
positive purification and development
while reality deep down you know nothing
is changing nothing is required to be
given up
and now no renunciation of the real kind
so you're just like playing in the sand
really emulating it Without Really
committing to it knowingly that you're
not going to commit to it at church on a
Sunday said my prayers yeah yeah exactly
yeah yeah
and and what is their poster of the
noble ones
it is the cleansing of the defiled mine
through the proper technique
and how is the defoul mind defiled mind
cleansed to the proper technique
so there is the case where disciple of
the number one's a noble disciple
recollects recollects the Buddha indeed
the blessed one is worthy rightly
self-awakened consummate in knowledge
and conduct well gone an expert with
regard to the world unexcelled as a
trainer for those fit to be tamed the
teacher of divine and human beings
awakens so he has faith in his teaching
in the teacher the teaching yeah as he
is recollecting like this his mind is
kind Joy arises the defilements of his
mind are abandoned just as when the head
is cleansed through proper technique
right and it gives that goes through
soap and so on yeah what what I said
exactly what people believed by washing
your head with the soap with this water
in that direction you're cleansing your
mind but it says yes to a technique of
but it says yes to a technique of
recollecting the Buddha the damages I'm
going the base of your right View
recollecting the quality of a vitamin
the path the knowledge you are cleansing
your mind by bringing up and thinking
about those contexts those themes
of of Enlightenment Awakening freedom
from suffering on the basis of your
right views on the basis of seeing what
your mind actually is uh then yes that
results in the actual purification like
what people believe of washing it you
know the the method and the emotions of
how you wash it and how you prostrate
like that that's how people believe it
but this is what actually cleans your
mind are you bowing down like this yeah
cleans the mind yeah exactly exactly
yeah it's the recollection of the Buddha
on the base of your right view that
cleans your mind yeah yeah so the right
themes the right contemplations clean
your mind
as we said so many times as the Buddha
said in many suitors what you often
think and ponder about that becomes the
direction of your mind it's an
inclination it slopes it goes that way
so if you often think in ponderable
Liberation suffering the Peril of
sensuality the mind will turn away from
those things that are contradictory to
that but there needs to be like yeah observed
but there needs to be like yeah observed
regularly
sustained thought to that yeah exactly
we thought about pondered on uh rickind
that is your Zeal towards that
inspiration towards thinking those
things that kind of initially go against
your experience and certainly against
the experience of a central household
life but if you think about them long enough
but if you think about them long enough
they will the values behind those themes
those contexts will take place we'll
take root will start to grow because it
because it
here you don't really hear about that
often I just think about the Buddha and
his qualities it's kind of well because
yeah people well first of all as with
many other suitors people ignore the
fact that you need to be assertable
first for that to apply to you haven't
ignored that fact then it becomes easy
to oh yeah of course we already do that
so it's taken for granted that everybody
already does that and it's great but you
realize well actually follow further in
the same Sota these are the results that
should follow if you do that rightly on
the base of the review so do you have
the results to follow
is your mind inspired because you think
you're saved by the Lord Buddha
or is your man inspired because it's
incapable of lasting aversion towards
very unfavorable circumstances and then
the confidence towards I cannot be
defiled internally confidence comes on
account of it is that you heal your
inspiration or because the Lord Buddha
is always looking over you and
everything will work out
it's different yeah yeah which one is it
or maybe not specifically such a kind of
personified idea of the Lord Buddha but
do you hold the belief that everything
will work out
everything will be fine for you where's
that belief rooted is an effectual
recognition of your right view so the
party so you know you are beyond the states of
so you know you are beyond the states of
parallel and so on
Factory recognition that purified states
of mind that you know for fact
like you see them
pure and pure you're avoiding pure you
cultivated Pure or is it just wishful
thinking everything will work out on the
basis of what the base of what you have
such observance
yeah you can start the event or
Imagining the Buddha yeah these images
maybe you won't do that but do you deep
down believe that everything worked out
okay but fine you have that belief no
problem what do you do in account with
do you like put that belief first and
then all the effort the renunciation
reflection giving up that you have to do
that you know you have to do if you want
to practice Dharma do you kind of try
your best and you know but they don't
believe that everything will work out
although you are not really putting the
effort first
or are you really putting there for
first and disregarding the belief
whether it's there or not doesn't matter
what matters is whether you make the
effort and that always comes back to that
and that always comes back to that
simile of the the the chicken that it
takes if a chicken even if she wishes every
if a chicken even if she wishes every
minute of her life may these chicks my
chicks Pierce safely from these shells
but she doesn't sit in the eggs long
enough well enough often enough they
won't and then you have the other chick
whether even she doesn't wish for the
chicken but if she doesn't wish for the
chicks to pierce out they will because
she is doing the work
and that's always like so are you
putting the work first or you believe
that everything work out work out and
every and you are doing your best or
you're putting that first
because otherwise it's a bit too much
pressure
yeah you do are you doing the chain I'm
supposed to do let's get empty again
these are like the obvious kind of Clean
Cut examples but you could if you
deserve the principle you could see how
it would apply to many of the
Contemporary things that are that are
down in place
purification through Mantra purification
to incense whatever so through
techniques through methods purification
through or I won't have to think
sustained Ponder and danger and develop
the context and reflect and get the
right view first I'll just do this
exercise pretty much I'll just watch my
nostrils like this walk like this attend
to this feel like this and then I'll be
purified but it's like the only way for
purification to occur
is if you already can and have seen the
signs of your mind the phenomenon the
chitanimity for what it is if you
basically have the right View without
the right view the the domain where
purification happens it's just invisible
to it and that's why often without the
Right View any such practice does kind
of imply to some degree
you know when everybody starts the
practice you know you're new to it you
get your ideas and the idea of
Enlightenment inside soda party it
always has almost like this requires
this magical leap like I'm doing all
this stuff I'm committed okay doing
these practices and then the Right View
will happen to me
means you don't really see where
purification is and when it happens
because that's what happens when you
purify it that's what the right view is
when the mind is purified enough
but in order to purify it enough you
can't just wish for it to happen on
account of these observances you're
doing
only if you see it where it needs to be
purified what it needs to be purified
if you start saying what the mind is
that's why it is the prerequisite for
the Right View
yeah and then you know exactly what the
practices then there is no more magical
leaps involved or doing this for this to
happen you know exactly wholesome
attention and wholesome intention
cultivating words and cleaning yes dirt
and cleanliness and you know you see
exactly what needs to be cleaned and how
and to what extent
that's when you can start
don't work yeah
that's at least when you know what the
work is
now you see it clearly and that's all
you know you you reason you measure the
task or this is what needs to be done
you see what it needs to be done and
then it's easy to do it because now you
see it
but when it's all like sort of
you know at arm's length with certain
kind of magical leaps in connection just
hoping for it to happen then
idiots yes we're thinking and then
whatever happens you don't even know if
it's good or bad important or
unimportant you're already bent on it
being the right thing so that's when
people start interpreting any mundane
stuff as spiritual stuff because of the
context of the spiritual practice
but if they didn't have the context of
the spiritual practice that they
developed their inspiration you would
just see it as the mundane stuff or just
some new experience a novelty this
novelty that there's nothing there's
nothing to it but no there's much more
to it because of my already pre-decided
belief that there will be a lot more to
it because I'm practicing and that does
go hand in hand with that with that view
that everything will work out
so whatever I'm doing on account of my
inspiration to practice Zama
doesn't matter whether I see it whether
it's directly related how it's related
whether it's bringing our wholesome to
increase wholesome to decrease or
wholesome to increase on wholesome it
doesn't matter if I see that clearly if
I fully understood it doesn't matter if
I see the sun it doesn't matter if I
have the right View
I do have the pure wholesome intention
to practice the dhamma thus whatever I
do in account of that it's towards the
goal of nibana and the Dharma and I'll
be fine
and that's a very dangerous view to have
because as we said in previous talks in
the suit that's one of the definitions
of the right view is knowing important
as important and unimportant is
unimportant without knowing that
people end up doing unimportant as
important and overlookingly important
and often people do Overlook like see
the world describes exactly how to come
in mind how to experience Joy how to
purify your mind if you have the right
View think these themes sustain them observe
think these themes sustain them observe
them make an observance out of them for
many people that's exactly as we said oh
yeah that's just thinking
that's not as important see the attitude
for somebody who would say well that's
just merely thinking about a Buddha
that's not as important there must be
something more important
and there you go you overlooked what's
actually important
and went further and new lost it
but that is what's important
do it long enough you see it
yeah that's what they're just thinking
that's just contemplation
anybody can do that yeah but how many
people actually do it like that how many
people do it on the basis of the Right
View
but exactly whoever reads that many
people would read that and it would you
you almost don't even read it anymore
you just oh yeah put it on the song of
course I approve of that
no no do You observe it do you make a
theme to ponder on these qualities do
you dig them up revisit them establish
your mind
basically develop inspiration towards
those not like when I say inspiration I
don't mean uplifting of Faith where
everything will work out I'm inspired no
inspiration to think more about you what
you've already been thinking to really
get even more clarity in regard to to
what needs to be understood
but again if you think that it's oh
that's just that that's obvious that's
self-evident you overlooked the important you see
you overlooked the important you see
this not so important I it's unimported
let's go let's go to the
um a second there is the case where
disciples no more uh Noble disciple
recollects the Dharma also you
know and all recollects
the Sangha
yes you see like recollects the Dharma
does not mean you wreck I recollect the
dhamma the dhamma is the great no
recollects any aspect practical aspect
of the Buddhist Enlightenment the
teacher what he teaches
so regulates the dhamma to recollecting
any relevant context
theme or account of which you kind of have the
or account of which you kind of have the
right view already that can now further
it even more
but yeah that dhamma is the great dam is
the greatest teacher no don't recollect
it in personal kind of glorifying sense
recollecting in the practice in the same
sense recollecting the quality of the
Buddha the teacher it's well expanded I
it's worth committing to personally it's
worth for me to commit to the teaching
of this teacher so yes there is some
Faith involved but only so that you can
do it and start seeing it for yourself
so it's not about
worshiping the Sangha no it's about
worshiping the Buddha either nor the
Sandra nor the dhamma the teaching the
great the great depicted let's bow to it
in it involving yourself personally with
it so that you can start doing it so
that you can become free from suffering
even and again all of these
Recollections don't require you to meet
the Buddha no the Sangha for that matter
you just recognize so yeah the teaching
freedom from suffering having obviously
understood enough initially
where the problem is where the mind is
develop the right view now recollect the
same recollect the quality of the Buddha
the teacher how what he said you should
do and practice and develop it's worth
because you can see it for yourself
already the benefits and the results of
it so just keep reminding yourself let's
say that there's a context then your
mind will
well it will become unable to to uh to
be defiled
and something I left out was when
recollecting the Dumber the simile is
like cleaning your body so regulating
the body is cleaning your head
body and recollecting the sun you will
be cleaning your clothes putting on new
clothes fresh clothes yeah and
so there is a case with a noble disciple
recollects his own virtues okay oh my
virtues are unbroken unspotted
unsplattered untarnished liberating
praised by the wise conducive to samadhi
to composure
as he's recollecting his virtue his mind
is calm Joy arises the defilements of
his mind are abandoned but just as when
Murray is cleansed through proper
technique now the example is cleaning so
that's the again that's the technique
recollection context on the basis of
factual sense restraint and not giving
into unwholesome Behavior
keeping the Verge unbroken recollecting
it gladness Joy Somali that is what
Somali is established context of the
right kind
and the technique
it's like the technique of cleaning the
mirror the mechanical technique of
cleaning the mirror
except you realize up there is nothing
mechanical can be done about it
you can that's the thing if you start
mechanically recollecting the virtue of
the dam of the sun's yeah exactly one
last and that's why all people need
something more palpable number tell me
what to do you know with my body with my
attention with my Sensations tell me
something more powerful because it was
uh recollect my own virtues
well yeah so do I keep five pieces no
eight pieces five pieces what is the
result today what is the result
uplifting where are my values yeah yeah
you're just like realizing where you're
right is it on the value of the shepherd
like I want this I do it I want that now
I do this or is it on the way no hold on
this observance of the precepts that it
needs to be undertaken like infinitely
for the rest of my life
and it said that before you know it's
better to take the five presets for the
rest of your life then eight precepts on
the weekend yeah
because you will feel the weight of it
the context of it and that's already a
better base is for then you can take it
within that and so on but you will never
go below five
but if you're just taking occasionally
picking and choosing your spiritual
practice becomes like the shepherd's
desires I want this oh now I have too
much of it now I want a spiritual
practice up until I forget anyone back
into this you know this and just
flopping from one to the other yeah un
beneficial one yeah
so there's the case with an old cycle
that collects the Davis
so yeah actually there are these divers
in these Heavens these great Kings and
so on
who have the power of others Creations
he thinks about all these other Heavens
Heavenly realms
whenever I said whatever conviction
or faith they they were endowed with
uh endowed with when falling away from
this life they rearose there in heaven
the same sort of conviction is present
in me as well whatever virtue they were
endowed with
when they when they died in this life
they rearosing yeah conviction I think
it means fake Faith whatever Faith they
had whatever virtue they had exactly
whatever factors their generosity there
exactly and whatever discernment they
had all those things are present within
me that's why those beings went to
heaven yeah so that's you you can
you can feel confident that the worst
case scenario If You Don't Take Your
Right View further you'll at least be in
the heavens
that's the worst case scenario which is
not a bad scenario from the human point
of view
I'm still going to a good place I'm
still well yeah right and even if you
say well but I don't you know I don't
see the devils and the Kings and so on
you have faith in the Buddha an account
of which you practiced and developed the
Right View so you see for yourself
freedom from suffering you see for
yourself the benefit to Faith virtue of
discernment now the same Source the
Buddha who taught you these things that
are kind of impossible to see you
realize the depth of the Dharma when you
get the right view you realize how it's
how it cannot be obtained by accident
how it is truly a miracle that sort of
you know the self-awakened one
discovered and told to others
and now he says these other things about
rewards in Heavens that I don't
necessarily see but I have absolutely no
basis to doubt it because what you know
what pertains to the core of your holy
life has been understood
and he came from the same source that
also says and see if you don't get
anywhere at least you'll be in heaven
the second after the Buddha in terms of
the sermon couldn't seem to heaven or
understand the Devils or anything
he had faith in them did it real because
obviously the Buddha said so but he
couldn't see any of it to the point of
that suta where
um he heard somebody asked him about he
heard that all these these Devils that
live many of them live on the single place no
many of them live on the single place no
space on the needle
and they don't feel crowded and confined
with each other because their minds are
so lofty and developed
thought what to make of it he said oh
it's because they practice the the like
they developed their minds over there
right and that was his answer like on
the basis of reasoning here and now he
didn't see the Devils he couldn't see
how and why he couldn't talk to them as
other some other monks could
and then the Davis had that and when I
told the Buddha to tell him that he was
wrong and actually he was their minds
developed during the human life
that's where the practice is now they're
enjoying benefits
and then they could have told it started
putting he's like oh yeah but he
couldn't see it for himself
so it's it's a kind of
um can be the extension of the faith but
it's also again just to calm your mind
down if there's pressure disturbances but you
if there's pressure disturbances but you
do have the right view but you might be
overwhelmed nevertheless illness
something's happening whatever else
hardships bearing too much of the elements is just
bearing too much of the elements is just
adding up
reflect on these things and you get some
ideas a result of it because as I said
it did come from the same Source the
source that taught you the right View
and not to suffer amid suffering
also talked about these other Rewards
that why why would he have a reason to
lie if he already showed you something
that no other teaching shows you it
doesn't require anything from it doesn't
require worship doesn't require some
weird kind of sacrificial just requires
good virtue which is good regardless of
religion not killing not stealing or
cheating not lying it's it's good
regardless of what your views are
sense restraint not engage in sensuality
that's verifiable here and now it's
burden it's unpleasant it's Peril it
results in more more weight all things
you can see for yourself
yes feed me from all those things and
it's always like one of the first come
and see for yourself when people ask
about your teaching come and see for
yourself don't by all means I urge you
to not take it merely on faith and
inspiration and how radiant I look or
something I'm going to put us into come and see
I'm going to put us into come and see
for yourself
the last bit is uh furthermore the
disciple of the noble ones Noble
disciple reflects thus as long as they
live the arrowheads abandon the taking
of life
abstain from The Taking of Life dwell
with their web weapons laid down and so
on compassionate for the welfare of all
living beings
today I too for this day and night
abandoning The Taking of life
uh compassionate for the welfare of all
living beings by by means of this factor
I emulate the Iran's and my poster will
be observed so by
so a noble disciple
he takes on this thing and says I'll
just do it for this day and night
and so on with um take you know not
stealing as long as they live the arrowheads
as long as they live the arrowheads
abandon unset of the
sexuality the sexual act live a
Celebrate life included refrain from the
sexual act that is the villager's way
today I too for this day night abandon
uncelibacy yeah so what's the difference
between somebody just claiming to do that for a
somebody just claiming to do that for a
day and night
and Noble disciples doing it for the day
night because obviously it implies
whenever the disciple will go back to
his life yeah so would become uncelibate
and so on if he doesn't want to practice
further but he's truthful
during that day and night okay why is he
truthful and the previous example wasn't
truthful
but he's not truthful from the start
and Noble disciples truthful why is that
what's the difference
so they both decide from the start
they're only going to do it for 24 hours
but what is truthful the other one isn't
because he understands what he
understands what he understands what
he's doing he understands that he's
cleansing the mind he's not he's not
doing it out of wishful thinking he
knows that he is cleansing the mind in
this so he has direct insight into the
behavior of another hand
into the mind of United exactly that's
exactly what it is that's what thought
about his understanding what Aaron and
chip is
that's the right View
now
tailoring and shaping your life your
decisions your intentions to fully
support the understanding of arahan's mind
the understanding of arahan's mind
is what nibana will be
it will it will result in demand
so when a noble disciple then says I
shall emulate
The Virtue the behavior of another hand
he understands exactly what that is yeah
so for that 24 hours he is actually
doing it
although he knows he won't sustain it
at least his recognition what he's doing
pertains directly to what what needs to
be done right so it's not like I just
take on this method this Behavior this
technique this observance
for the wishful thinking of being an
arahunt but I don't see for myself what
other hand is yeah Noble disciple does
he takes he takes that practice other
people yeah he's the only one they can yeah
yeah he's the only one they can yeah
that's what remains perpetually
available they write to you you might
not engage with it all the time as there
were cases of careless sodapanas in the
suitors lay people they you know
drinking and doing this and that
but the view that they can
perpetually turn to and take on the view
of arunachi that then they can commit to
the Jews if the sense of urgency sort of
produce them in that direction that
remains because that's what sotopana is
having that view accessible the view of
where the mind is
what the right timing is actually what
the Escape is